So um
say somebody's
keeping the precepts training in the
eight precepts practicing senses trained
you know household monk doesn't matter
the question is um
are there times where it's more or less
appropriate for thinking and contemplating things
for thinking and contemplating things
that Chitta doesn't want to think about.
So are the times where you should force
it to think about things and are the
times where you should like okay now I
won't I won't be forcing it how to uh
discern where that line is
well you should force it if you see that
if you leave it alone it's going to
start inclining towards sensuality
it will delight in the world if if
that's its its um
its slant at the moment then you need to
do something about that. But
>> if you see
that is not there if I just leave the
mind on its own it's not going to move
towards those things then you actively
trying to kind of force it to think
about it will just be like hitting an
animal that's not misbehaving.
If without if you choose to not
contemplate, you already know
you already know
it's already implicit that by not
bringing up certain topics, the mind
will continue, the animal will continue
walking >> outside of the boundaries mentally,
>> outside of the boundaries mentally,
verbally, and then eventually
physically. Yeah.
>> So you bring up those reflections,
topics, uh death, illness, the unpleasant stuff
uh death, illness, the unpleasant stuff
that the mind doesn't want to think
about, liabilities and so on. You bring
that up to the extent just to
undo neutralize that passion towards walking
neutralize that passion towards walking
towards the pastures it shouldn't go.
But if it's not walking there, you
should actually not bring it up.
So you can't be like um uh blindly bound
with the duty of I must contemplate and
bring it up regardless of the basis or
the state of the mind where it's in
>> because that will then be that sense of
duty will then be the strongest
inclination that's dominating you at the
time. >> So it will be that will come out of the
>> So it will be that will come out of the
mind being restless. M
so you look where your mind is at
without contemp without without bringing
up contemplations like oh is it uh
leaning towards sensuality complacency
laziness or no it seems it seems all
right seems balanced enough then I don't
need to bring anything up
>> when it starts to lean you will know
>> yeah because I think the problem is you
might expect a super defined
confirmation that it's not leaning in
those ways,
>> but it's just the absence of leaning in
those is the confirmation.
>> That's that's the kind of that
peripheral discernment you have to keep
working on.
>> Yeah.
>> And getting the hints of is it leaning
or not, not the specific palpable proof.
>> It's not going to tell you like, oh, I'm
not leaning anymore.
>> No. No. Because that's not where the
mind is. Um,
Um,
I guess I I've often heard people ask
similar questions and of something
that's brought up is the uh the second
arrow and then how your how someone
could turn their kind of contemplations
into this kind of
>> oh who shot me?
>> Uh, you know,
>> why am I doing this? I have to think
about my whole past or uh understand
Well, that actually
>> that would fall under the the very well
under what you said.
>> So if if say some suffering arose and
you're pressured to analyze it, who,
what, why, how to prevent it,
>> that's mind going into the wrong
pastures already.
>> It's a full-on obsessive pressure,
irritation, compulsion. So it's like, so
now I should not think about those
things. I should just
>> pull the mind back basically not let it
not provide it.
>> Yeah. And that's that's what it's about
developing the criteria of the mind as
the thing that determines the practice.
Whereas when you don't see that Yeah.
You will take on this duty of
contemplating things as if that
independently as an ideal is what needs
to be done rather than seeing it's only
to the extent that it influences the
mind does that need to be done
>> because you the mind is where the
problem is. It's not in the fact that
you failed to contemplate.
>> So how do I how do I see my mind? How do
I get to see that? What do I do?
Well, ask yourself what is like you said
before, what is the main kind of
effortless inclination
that that would present itself
without you putting it there.
>> Mhm.
>> So if now
the thing that I'm being pulled towards
is contemplating
>> Mhm.
>> not sensuality or will well those are
the signs of your mind now. Mhm.
>> So it's whatever is is manifesting.
>> So should I contemplate in that specific
scenario if I'm pulled towards
contemplating? >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Like you shouldn't do what the mind is
pulling you to do. But if you're afraid
of like oh so does that mean I'll become
mindless? Well, you're already the the
seeing of that pressure
>> towards contemplation
is what you should be reflecting on
>> is a more right contemplation.
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> Right. So if the mind is pulling you
towards contemplation, don't just take
it for granted and start walking with it
in that direction.
>> Contemplate the danger,
>> but recognize the pulling mind doesn't
matter what is pulling you towards and
that's actually contemplation just not
on your own terms.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
I mean, it also might be worth
mentioning the
level of ambiguity that comes from
um not doing it on your own terms. And
>> so, yeah, because
>> because you won't
it doesn't feel right.
>> Yeah.
>> Like it feels more right to contemplate
when the mind is pressuring you to
contemplate. So it feels kind of wrong to
So it feels kind of wrong to
>> but then ask yourself what type of
feeling right is that? Is it the same
feeling right of when it's inclining to
sensuality and you give into that?
That's the type of feeling right. It's
because it's helping you like it it's
helping you do that contemplation
because that's where it wants to go
already. So if that's what's happening you
So if that's what's happening you
realize well you're not taming it you're
giving into it. from safety.
from safety.
>> Yeah. It's like going with the grain.
That's literally the meaning of the
expression. It's like where the grain
already is,
>> you're going there feels right because
>> to satisfy the compulsion basically.
>> Yeah.
So what about if you you you've been
training in contemplation
every day so on you know for a long time
and then it it's that's the what the
mind enjoys doing now uncovering things
uncovering issues you know
>> uh your defilements
>> am I liable to suffering
>> you know there's that uh one statement
somewhere the Buddhist said was that he
knew two qualities when he was striving
was discontent with unh wholesome with
wholesome qualities.
>> Yeah. With discontent with unh wholesome
states that
>> No, with wholesome qualities.
>> With sorry with wholesome
>> discontent with wholesome qualities and
unrelenting >> effort. Yeah.
>> effort. Yeah.
>> Effort. So it was like you would be
contemplating, uncovering things,
destroying defilements as virtuous and
feeling >> the joy of that. And the mind is
>> the joy of that. And the mind is
this is great.
>> Yeah. And yet he he's saying
I'm discontent with that. So he's seeing
the mind's contentment and then he's
being discontent with that and saying
well no we need to dig more.
>> Yeah.
>> We need to make more effort
>> as as the Buddhist.
>> Right. Right. But the always the thing
would be like it would be against the
grain. it wouldn't be on your terms that
the mind wanted to uncover things,
wanted to like um be discontent and you
went with it. On account of that, it's
it's the mind was going towards a
direction of contentment and then you
need to actually make an effort to see
wait even in this there is still
>> uh dissatisfaction there is still
inadequacy. >> Complacency.
>> Complacency.
>> Yeah. The mind gets complacent basically
>> complacent to see that.
>> Yeah. But of course like that would be
complacent now with things that are
actually wholesome.
It it wouldn't be complacency with like
a normal person being complacent with
mean will would mean they would be
tolerating sensuality and things like
that. >> So being complacent with your withdrawal
>> So being complacent with your withdrawal
from sensuality
which is not in itself our for example.
So relentless effort it's um basically
relentlessly not allowing actions out of any
not allowing actions out of any
layer of compulsion.
>> It's not relentlessly grab the
compulsion and run with it relentlessly
and never stop which is how initial it
will be taken. Yeah.
>> No, it's like whenever compulsion is
discerned relentlessly,
>> diligently, you never willingly accept
it. >> You always re reestablish perspective in
>> You always re reestablish perspective in
regard to it. So if one can think about
um contemplate and and the actually
reflect on asavas and uncover asavas
without any grain of compulsion coming
from the mind then yes that's what's
meant with that pure relentless
u training on the right level
>> but if one does it out of this like
mental force of pressure if I do it I'll
get rid of it that's just um that's kind
of falls off the the right context.
Yeah. And if you ask yourself honestly,
what takes more effort
>> to
>> to not feed the compulsion
>> to go with it or to say no to it.
>> Yeah. Doesn't matter what the object of
it is.
>> Even if it's the dama.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
So then by not following the compulsion
towards quote unquote dharma
reflections, you are actually practicing the dharma.
you are actually practicing the dharma.
>> Exactly. That that would be the dharma.
Non-passion, non aversion.
>> Yeah.
>> Non- restlessness.